In order to struggle more effectively against the inhabitants of
Dunkirk, we too began to build the vessel in question and their number
increased rapidly under the urgent advice of our great Admiral Tromp.
(~De Jonge~, Vol. I, pp. 388 and 389.) Later on they were built of
larger size.

[Sidenote: III 18]

As has just been said the frigate was imported into France by the
inhabitants of Dunkirk; thence it passed into England, in 1741,
(~Holmes~, p. 121); all the same, this latter country had already had
some of smaller size in 1646.

The frigates played an important part in the Anglo-American war.

Fire was one of the greatest enemies of wooden ships. Hence recourse
was had to this element from the earliest times, in order to destroy an
enemy’s fleet. It was not enough to throw burning pitch; more effective
means were invented and the Ancients were already using fireboats to
set fire to the hostile fleet.

Time will not be wasted in conjectures about the fireships of the
Ancients, which could only have been ordinary vessels. A summary
description will rather be given of those used in the XVIIth century
they being the only ones mentioned in Witsen’s well known work, pp. 166
and 167.

Vessels of rather small size acted as fireboats, preferentially flutes
or pinnaces. Later, “spiegelschepen” of 70 or 80 lasts were used.
These vessels had a smooth continuous deck in which were made holes
having an area of about 1.5 square feet. A trough starting from the
poop ran forward for the entire length of the vessel, with side troughs
leading athwartships, in a word, a train was formed which would let
the fire run easily and quickly throughout the ship. For this purpose,
the troughs were filled with a mixture composed half of gunpowder by
volume, quarter of saltpetre and the remaining quarter made up of equal
parts of resin and sulphur, the whole mixed with a little linseed oil.

The troughs thus filled were covered with shavings which, in their
turn, disappeared under faggots of light branches soaked in a mixture
of resin, cod-liver oil, powder and saltpetre. In addition to this,
the vessel was filled with other inflammable materials; the deck and
the inside walls were smeared with grease and covered with a layer of
finely powdered resin.

Sometimes the fireships were loaded with open barrels filled with
shavings soaked in tar. Special care was also taken that all ports and
hatches should be left open so as to give plenty of draught.

In order more surely to have the fireship catch the enemy’s vessel,
strong grapnels were attached to the end of the bowsprit and to the
ends of the yards; these grapnels could be detached by means of ropes
laid along the ship.

In order to deceive the enemy and to save appearances, quaker guns were
stationed in the ports. Two iron guns only were placed aft for defence
against attacks.

A large trap was made in the poop to allow the crew to quit the vessel,
after having lighted the fire and let go the grapnels, and to get away
in a launch attached to the fireship underneath the trap.

The service with fireships was naturally a perilous task, so only the
bravest men were selected for this duty and they, on account of the
great danger incurred, received double pay.

In case of need, the fireships were started straight at the enemy, so
that the latter’s ship was taken face on and not by the side. Under
these conditions, the rigging of the two vessels became entangled at
once and it became impossible then to separate them.

The fireships were only old ships as a rule, yet new vessels were
sometimes employed, for the construction of which, as Witsen says, “a
very ordinary, very light and very inflammable wood was used.”

Externally the fireships did not differ from ordinary vessels; anything
else would not have been practical, because the enemy would have
recognized them at once under these conditions. Their crew was as few
in numbers as possible and every precaution was taken to allow it to
leave the vessel as soon as the latter was well on fire and had reached
the desired point.

[Sidenote: II 158]

[Sidenote: II 101]

The changes made in our war ships during the XIXth century are
sufficiently well known; consequently it will not be necessary to
dwell on them. Nothing more will be said than this: that the sheer of
these vessels became less, that the stem and the sternpost approached
more nearly the vertical and that the old ornaments disappeared almost
entirely.

[Sidenote: II 165]

Toward the end of the XVIIIth century, the rounded shape of the stern
was adopted, according to the English fashion. It was the death blow
to the old square stern ship, but already, long before that, it had
been called _ship of war_. This new denomination changed nothing in its
construction.

Our shipbuilding had gone to pieces under the French occupation, and
the continental blockade completed the ruin. Still, toward the end of
the first half of the XIXth century it succeeded in reviving. It is
true that in 1824 only three ships, measuring in all 1440 tons, were
built; but, in 1827, this number had already gone up to 59 vessels with
a total tonnage of 19,758 tons. These data relate only to vessels of
more than 100 tons. (~Koenen~, p. 101.)

In 1853, says M. Koenen, there were in the province of Groningen 89
shipyards for both inland and ocean navigation. In Friesland, there
were large yards at Harlingen and at Lemmen devoted exclusively to the
construction of sea-going vessels. In North Holland, ocean shipping
was under construction at Amsterdam, Medenblik, Monnickendam, Muiden
and Nieuwendam. Shipbuilding was flourishing at Rotterdam, Schiedam,
Alblasserdam and Dordrecht.

In this same year, 1853, adds the author above named, 125 ships built
in our country were registered, and our merchant marine included 1971
vessels with a total tonnage of 224,432 lasts (= 448,864 tons).

Steam, too, had appeared among us during the first half of the XIXth
century and sailing vessels for this reason were relegated to the
background. The adoption of iron for the frames of ships also brought
about great changes; but the importance of this new material was not
everywhere sufficiently taken into account, and many shipyards which
continued to hold to building in wood underwent a rapid decline.
Others, on the contrary, which had taken up iron construction from the
moment of its appearance, became largely prosperous and contributed
greatly toward maintaining the ancient fame of our naval architecture.

The first iron ship turned out in the Netherlands was built by Fop
Smit, who appears also to have been the inventor of iron masts. The
first Dutch steamboats were built at Feyenoord (1834-1835) in the yard
which now belongs to the Society of Naval and Mechanical Constructions.
(See _Gedenkboek Kon, Instituut van Ingenieurs_, p. 209, etc.)

The revolution wrought by the introduction of steel in the construction
of war ships is sufficiently well known; but these vessels have lost
all character of their own and they can no longer be recognized except
by the flag which they fly. Such is the present situation for ocean
navigation, and such will also be the situation for inland navigation.
Here too steel has been adopted for the construction of the frames of
vessels, and the old forms are passing away to give place to types
which will soon be in general use.

But, when that time comes, river boats will also have lost all national
character and search will be made in vain to know what were the
characteristics of the past. And yet, in spite of the uniformity which
even now exists, the vessels which Holland has turned out can still
always be recognized by their solid and elegant forms.

And may it thus ever be; may our builders ever carry higher the fair
fame of Dutch naval construction; and may Dutch capital also continue
to second them and to understand that the strength of our land lies in
a flourishing marine. But the latter needs in its turn excellent lines
of communication; the XIXth century, as we all know, has seen the rise
of new communications by water and the improvement of the old lines;
the obstacles, arising from insufficient depth in the channels leading
to our commercial centres, have disappeared, and it has become possible
for us to compete with foreign nations in the arena of the construction
of large ships.



FOOTNOTES:

  [4] The Dutch marine owes its prosperity not to the beauty of form of
       its ships, but to the value of its limited personnel, to the
       sobriety of its seamen and to the innate cleanliness of the
       Dutch people.

  [5] On this point, they (the English) openly defy all other nations
       and believe themselves to be unequaled on the ground of
       shipbuilding.

  [6] _Western Influence on the Cultivation, Mode of living and
       Agriculture of the Children of the North (Norwegians and other
       Scandinavians) in the Time of the “Vikings”_, by ~Alexander
       Bugge~.

  [7] It is the opinion of most authors that the Frisians have the
       honor of having made shipbuilding flourish again in the
       Netherlands.

  [8] “How _cogs_ were built in the past, and how much they have
       changed with the passage of time, just as in our day (the time
       of the writer) furthermore, the shape of ships is seen to be
       undergoing constant modifications.” (P. 364.)

  [9] The _statie_ was a sort of secondary bulwark at the stern, rising
       quite high above the rail. The tiller swung from side to side in
       an opening made in the bottom plank of the _statie_ and above
       the rail at the stern.

  [10] The “arcasse” includes the sternpost and the transoms. It
       belongs to square-sterned vessels only.

  [11] The best and surest means of avoiding a too great draught of
       water consists in widening the ships. An endeavor should be made
       to realize this programme, seeing how shallow our passes are.
       According to the opinion of experienced pilots who have sounded
       the passes conscientiously, it is not possible to bring ships
       drawing more than 20 feet through the “Goeree” pass, or ships
       drawing about an equal amount through the Texel, or more than 13
       feet through the Meuse. This is why it has happened more than
       once that war vessels of the State, of fine lines and deeply
       ballasted so as to facilitate manœuvering under sail, could not
       gain the open sea at low tide or in calm weather, to the great
       detriment of the country, while outside, the lowest tier of guns
       could not be used because it was too near the water.

  [12] Several years ago, by reason of the shallowness of our rivers
       and passes, an attempt was made, so far as it was possible, to
       raise our large, deep draught ships by means of empty casks, so
       that they could reach the open sea. But this process required an
       infinite time and great labor just to put the casks into place.

  [13] “The vessel which sails to the West or the South shall have the
       bow covered with copper to protect it against the teredo”.


It was seen in the preceding chapter that it was not until the second
half of the XVIIth century that the construction of vessels of war,
as such, was begun in Holland. Up to that moment merchant ships were
equipped and used for military purposes. In proportion as commerce
developed and as dangers from enemies at sea increased, the armament of
merchant ships became more and more important. So, personal interest
was the cause of partially equipping merchantmen as men of war. It was
for this reason that the East India Company built ships which may be
considered as types of the kind.

Consequently it was just the largest merchant vessels which were most
changed as time rolled by. The old types are, therefore, no longer
found in this category of vessels; it is among the small craft that
they are best preserved.

The oldest type of Dutch ship is the “Koggeschip” (Cog) from which are
descended the “Krayers” and “Hulken”. These vessels are all clinker
built. The “Barges”, “Baertsen”, etc. appeared in the XVth century.
Their planking was smooth. They gradually drove out the “Krayers” and
“Hulken”, from which they really differed little in form.

At the end of the XVth century are found the “Kraak” (carack or
galleon) which came to us from the nations of the South, just as we
took from them the “Spiegelschip” (a square-sterned vessel) at the
close of the XVIth century. The names of “Barges”, etc. now give place
to the “Koffen” (koffs) and “Smakken” (smacks); but the old forms do
not disappear by reason of this fact; the same types of vessels merely
change their name as the result of a few changes in details. It is
thus that of the “Tjalken” (tialks), which are not mentioned by Witsen
although they existed in his day and were then called “Smalschepen”
or “Wijdschepen”. Several other examples of this sort could be given.
The likeness of form is even so striking that, at the beginning of the
XIXth century, our fleet still showed perfectly the types of Witsen’s
time. The changes introduced were merely those of detail.

In examining the old types, which are now still in use, it is well
not to lose sight of the fact that our ships have, during the XIXth
century, increased greatly their length and beam and proportionally
also their draught as the result of the improvements of our navigable
highways and the digging of new channels.

The result of this has been the falling off of certain types, to which
the appearance of iron in shipbuilding has also largely contributed.

For other types, the improvement of the navigable highways and the
creation of ports have brought about their complete disappearance.
Thus the construction of the “Bommenhaven” will soon have, as its
consequence, the total disappearance of the old “Bommen” of which more
will be said further on (fishing boats).

The smaller boats will give, under these conditions, the best idea
of the old forms, and, as has been seen in what precedes, the most
beautiful specimens will be found among the fishing boats. The fishing
vessels best reveal the origin of the forms of our ships, so a special
chapter will be devoted to this kind of craft.

It has been seen that the essential difference between merchant
ships and men-of-war was marked by the narrow deck of the former
which allowed the size of the crew to be reduced (~Witsen~, pp. 54,
263, 266), and it has been told that the Dutch were always quoted as
examples in this matter. It is thus that the “Vliebooten” (flyboats)
appeared, the precursors of the “Fluiten” (flutes), which are known in
England by the name of the “Dutch Flight”.

Trips both to northern and southern countries give rise to changes from
which are developed a great number of types of boats all of which are
derived, however, from a same fundamental type. ~Witsen~ writes on this
subject (page 53).

“Noortsche deelhaelders laeden het meest wanneer na den vierkante
hellen, kooren schepen en die op stukgoederen aenleggen, als ze
rondtachtig zijn en veel springen. Oost en Noortsvaerders die grove
waeren laeden zijn grooter in ’t gemeen als die stukgoederen wijnen en
diergelijke laeden gelijk ook de zouthaelders”[14].

These are all variations of a same type of vessel.

When the size of ships increased, it was necessary to make them still
more bulging on account of the limited depth of the arms of the
sea, and this brought about the disappearance of differences in the
fundamental forms.

Thus we read in ~Van Yk~ (page 348).

“Maar als men hiertegen aanmerkt dat wegens de doorgaans ondiepe
gronden en lastvoerens wil alle schepen van tijd tot tijd vierkanter
werden gebouwd sulks dat heden desen aangaande niet so veel onderscheid
tusschen d’een en d’andere soort van schepen als wel voor dezen
gevonden werd. Want een hedendaags welgebouwde kaag sal in Lasten te
voeren ’t Smalschip dat in Lengte, Wijdte en Holte daaraan gelijk
is, weinig wijken willen. En de Damschuit die wel gemaakt is sal den
Damlooper bijna ook evenaren konnen.”[15]

The narrow deck of merchant vessels had still another origin
which referred to the way of gauging vessels and gave rise to the
construction of strongly bulging ships.

~Witsen~ says (p. 160) on this point:

“Het uitbreecken deser schepen (Noortsvaerders) voor en achter bracht
hier in den schipper profijt aan dat ze vele goederen meer stouden als
de maat der schepen hielt.”[16]

This applies especially to boats going to load wood or grain at the
Baltic ports, on account of the tolls which had to be paid to the King
of Denmark, tolls of which the amount was determined by the treaty of
1647, by calculating the capacity of the vessel in terms of the length,
the beam on deck and the depth of hold. But, when this treaty was
modified in 1666, this unsightly way of building and this exaggerated
bulging gradually disappeared (werd dit mismaekt bouwen en geweldigh
uitspringen achterwege gelaten). (~Witsen~, p. 160.)

[Sidenote: III 16]

Nevertheless, the construction of large numbers of merchant ships
with narrow decks was still persisted in and, even at the beginning
of the XIXth century, “Fluitschepen” (flutes) are still met with. A
beautiful model of one of these “Dutch Flights” exists at the museum of
antiquities at Dordrecht.

The greater bulging of merchant vessels kept pace with the
straightening of the sternpost and stem. On another side, the idea that
the volume of the submerged part of a vessel should be reduced to a
minimum, was abandoned toward the end of the XVIIth century.

[Sidenote: II 149]

[Sidenote: II 153]

The straightening of the sternpost brought about the shortening of
the beakhead which, at the beginning of the XVIIth century, measured
one-fifth of the total length of the vessel and only one-eighth of this
length at its end. This difference is clearly seen by comparing the
Zierikzee model with that of the “Bleijswijk”. The beakhead, which had
come down to us from ancient times (~Van Yk~, p. 103), was used only
“als Heimelijke gevoeg-plaatsen” (as a W. C.) for the crew, and those
who had been guilty of some unimportant misdemeanor were also shut
up there, as ~Van Yk~ says (p. 104), “des devotie des overspelenden
zeewaters” (at the mercy of the waves).

Fire was the great enemy of our merchant ships. The stoppage of leaks
was also more difficult for these vessels than for men-of-war because
it was impossible, as a rule, on the former to reach the leak from the
inside and through the cargo.

Water tight bulkheads did not exist, but, for all that, the stoppage of
the leak was none the less indispensable. ~Witsen~ tells us how
it was all handled (p. 276), and, after explaining how a fire was put
out, he continues thus:

“Wanneer een geschoten gat onder water van binnen niet gestopt kan
worden, hetzij den last in den weg is of anderzins, wordt een man
buiten boord met een prop in de hant op een plankje gezet, daar een
dreg aan vast is, die hem onder water haalt. En aldus stopt of dekt hij
de opening. Men geeft hem een geoliede lap in den mont on het water uit
het lichaem te weeren”[17].

Before going on to the classification, properly so called, of the
principal categories of vessels which have just been sketched out,
a few more remarks, about the ship in general and a few details in
particular, should be made.

The old builders of wooden vessels determined the ship’s length by
the work for which it was intended. This length was measured from the
forward side of the stem to the after side of the sternpost. The beam
and the depth were deduced from the length; the beam being taken equal
to one-fourth of the length, and for the depth, one foot was taken for
each 10 feet of length, at the point where the vessel’s height was
least. It was only for esthetic reasons that the sternpost was made
higher than the stem.

When the keel was laid down, the sternpost and the stem put up, the
wing transom was made fast to the fashion timbers, then the main frame
and the frame at the junction of the stem were reared. Another frame
was raised between the main frame and the sternpost. “Centen” (thin
flexible boards, called ribands in English) were then made fast to
these frames so as to determine in this way the shape of the ship and
to deduce therefrom the other frames.

According to ~Van Yk~ (p. 77), these boards are not called
“centen”, but “certen”, because the form of the vessel is fixed by
means of these boards and made “certain”. Other authors pretend that
the word comes from “Kanten” or “Kenten” from the word “bekendheid”
(knowledge).

The shape of the ship was thus determined by trial after having
settled, in the first place, on the main frame and the length. The
smaller the vessel, the more sheer it had and the more ribands were
required exactly to determine its shape.

On the other hand it was customary to give the ship some sheer
(zeegte), that is: to make it higher at the ends than at the middle.
This sheer was obtained, after setting the ribands, by means of
sheerstrakes of which the fastening was begun at the lowest point
of the height of the ship. These sheerstrakes rose forward at the
rate of 1 inch for every 6 feet of length, and aft at the rate of 5
inches for every 6 feet. The wales which served to protect the ship
were laid according to the sheerstrakes. The sheer in large vessels
(spiegelschepen) was gradually reduced and the effort was made
insensibly to build ships with a flat deck in imitation of England and
later of America. The sheer still exists in boats for inland waters,
like the “Tjalken”, “Poonen”, etc. Only one wale or bend is used for
small vessels, the larger ones, such as the “Tjalken” and “Smakken”
require three bends superposed.

It is noticed, as a rule, that the bends became lighter in the XVIIIth
century, just as did the sternpost and the stem. The engravings which
show boats prior to 1500, show also several equidistant bends, and it
was only at the end of the XVIth century that the single bends of later
days are seen to appear. Moreover, it is certain that the improvement
of the navigable highways was one of the causes of the lighter
construction of ships.

These old engravings show that the planking is in very short pieces
so as to avoid marked curves; but, in order to give, all the same,
sufficient stiffness to the vessel, many bends became necessary.

[Sidenote: II 138]

In the old shipbuilding, where the pieces of the planking nailed
together clinker ways make the construction more solid, the bends were
exceptional. The old “Koggeschepen” (Cogs), for example, had none, but
the reproduction of a small boat preserved at the church at Diemer
shows them.

These wales are then supported by round wooden brackets which are still
found in a few old “Poonen”.

In the matter of the wales, the rule was that when the vessel was seen
from in front they seemed to be convex, with the convexity on top,
whereas, seen from the side, they look concave, that is, with the
convexity underneath.

It has been said in what precedes that the method of ribands (“centen”)
was abandoned for large ships, about the middle of the XVIIth century,
and that, after that time, work was done from sketches in putting up
the frames and in building the ship.

The rudder was handled by means of a tiller, and on large vessels this
is often held up by a piece of wood (luierwagen) which is still seen on
many small inland vessels.

In order readily to work the tiller of large vessels, a hole was cut
in the poop deck immediately over the free end of the tiller in its
middle position. A lever passed upward through this hole and was hung
on a pivot of which the axis lay fore and aft. The lower end of the
lever was attached to the free end of the tiller while the upper end
was loose. By swinging the top of the lever to one side or the other
of the ship, a corresponding motion was given to the tiller and so to
the rudder. This manœuvre was, naturally, not easy in heavy weather
and required assistance. A pulley, around which ran a rope or steering
line having one end made fast to the tiller, was set in the deck so as
better to operate the rudder. (~Witsen~, p. 274, 2d column.)

This rope, which was served by two men, formed with the pulley the
precursor of the steering wheel which appeared on the continent in
the XVIIIth century, after having been already in use in England, as
certain authors try to make out.

It is claimed sometimes that the rudder could only swing a little to
either side. This, however, is a mistake. ~Witsen~ says, as a matter of
fact, p. 58: “The greater the swing of the rudder, the harder is the
manœuvre”. It is evident that Witsen would have said nothing about the
swing if it had been small. It follows clearly from the quotation from
~Van Yk~ (p. 121) in regard to the “luierwagens” that the helmsman must
have put forth a great deal of strength: “Hij (de luierwagen) diend
om de Roerpen, aan ’t vooreinde t’ ondersteunen nademaal deze, wegens
deszelfs langte, om sig selven te dragen immers _om ’t geweld dat de
man_ te Roer daaraan verrichten moet, uit te staan; al te zwak soude
wezen”[18].

Finally, M. Bouguer (1746) says in his work, p. 83, “that the rudder
should make with the prolongation of the keel an angle of about 55°
44´, etc.”.

Hence it is incorrect to say that the swing of the rudder could only
reach a few degrees. (~Paris~, vol. 4, p. 221.)

Furthermore, vessels should be able to come about more quickly in our
rivers, with their narrow channels and small depth of water, hence the
rudder should be able to swing more than a few degrees.

On small inland boats, the rudder is frequently lengthened on reaching
shallow water. This elongation was made by means of an isolated board
or a movable part (~Van Yk~, p. 221), a thing which happens still very
often at the present time.

If the tiller can be turned entirely above the bulwarks, which is
called in Dutch “geen statie voeren” (without statie), the vessel is
said to have a _draai over boord_ in contradistinction to vessels with
“statie”. The “statie” means the part of the bulwarks which rises above
the tiller[19].

The tiller passes in this case through an opening in the “statie”,
which prevents the rudder being brought hard over.

The length of the lee-boards is taken at twice the depth of the hold.

As many rivers and lakes are lacking in depth, the length of the
lee-boards is reduced for inland vessels, in order to prevent them
from touching bottom, consequently their width was increased.

The lee-boards for the ocean and for the rivers of Zealand are long and
narrow.

New modifications were made in the rigging of vessels toward the middle
of the XVIIIth century. The small bowsprit disappeared in order to make
place for the fore-masts which have remained in use since that time.

[Sidenote: III 145 etc.]

The rigging of the large vessels is sufficiently well known. It is
desired merely to dwell on the fact that fore-masts have been placed
wrongly on various models of the XVIIth century.

A vessel of which the planking is rabbetted into the stem is called a
“vaartuig”. The “Aak” (ake) is a boat without a stem and its planking
forms a plane up to the bow. The planking ends then at the plane in
front. If this occurs for a “Tjalk”, there is obtained what is known as
an “Aak Tjalk”.

When the after deck is raised so as to come up to the level of the main
rail, the vessel is said to be supplied with a “paviljoen”. Thus, for
example, a “Statiepaviljoenpoon”, is a “poon” with a raised deck. If
the after deck be not raised, the vessel is simply a “Statiepoon”.

Vessels can be grouped, then, in the following way:


CLASSIFICATION OF SHIPS

  I. WAR VESSELS.

  II. MERCHANTMEN.
       ~A~) For over seas trade;
       ~B~) For coasting trade and tidal streams.

  III. FERRIES.

  IV. BOATS FOR SUNDRY USES AND NOT BELONGING TO THE PRECEDING GROUPS.

  V. BOATS FREQUENTING THE UPPER PARTS OF RIVERS (BOVENLANDERS).
       ~A~) For the Rhine;
       ~B~) For the Meuse;
       ~C~) For the Upper Rhine and the basin included between the Rhine
            and the Meuse.

  VI. FISHING VESSELS.
       ~A~) For deep sea fishing;
       ~B~) For the coasting and river fisheries.


I.

WAR VESSELS.

In the matter of the evolution of the war ship, properly so-called, the
reader needs merely to be referred to the preceding chapters.

Before about 1675, there were, as a first war ship proper: the
_Pinasschip_ (Pinace) and later the _Spiegelschip_ (a square stern
ship). The square sterned _Spiegel_ disappeared and then round sterns
were again taken up, whence resulted the war ship called _Schip
van oorlog_. At the beginning, this class of vessels was made up
exclusively of ships with two decks. At the end of the XVIIth century,
however, a few types with three decks were built in the Netherlands.

Use was often made of the “Fluitschip” (flute or transport), of
ships of the East India Company (“Oost-Indische Compagnie schip”),
of “yachts” (“Jachten”) and of various sorts of vessels of less
importance, as auxiliary war ships, and of tenders (“Boeier”), galliots
(“Galjoot”), galeas (“Galeas”), “Bommen”, kuffs (“Koffs”) and smacks
(“Smaks”) as coast defence vessels.

All these vessels belong rather to the category of merchant ships and
will be described in the next chapter.

Among the types imitated from abroad there may be mentioned the
_Fregat_ (frigate), and later the _Brik_ (brig), the _Schooner_ and the
_Bark_.


II.

MERCHANT VESSELS.

~A~) _For over seas navigation._

The oldest merchant ship was the cog “Koggeschip”, from which are
descended the “Hulken” and “Krayers”. The planking of these ships is
clinker laid. Then vessels were built with more nearly rounded bottoms
and the carvel-built side appeared in the second half of the XVth
century. The resulting type was the _Barge_ or “Baertze”.

Meanwhile, the construction of castles was begun on these ships, just
as on the old cogs. These castles became gradually more important,
imitating what had been done on the Spanish, Portuguese and Genoese
ships. A type of vessel which, in accordance with the Spanish model,
carried large castles was the _Carack_ or _Galleon_ (“Kraak”)·

This vessel disappeared from our country in the course of the
XVIth century, at the end of which appeared the flyboats (“Vlie or
Vlietbooten”) called later Flutes (“fluiten”).

These vessels departed from the preceding types by having a marked
tumble in of the topsides. Hence the hull was full and the deck was
narrow. The flutes were the merchantmen “_par excellence_” up to the
beginning of the XIXth century.

The “Spiegelschip” also appeared toward the end of the XVIth century;
it acted as a merchantman in the same way as the similar vessel of the
Mediterranean. This vessel was called, at the beginning of the XVIIth
century, Pinnace (“Pinasschip”).

The Pinnace became more rounded in the second half of the XVIIth
century; it carried also a more nearly vertical stern and a smaller
beakhead. From it came the East India Company’s ship (“Oost-Indisch
Compagnie Schip”).

The flutes continued to hold their own alongside of the various types
of vessels, but changes were made to adapt them better to the use
for which they were intended, and so it was that the Noordvaerder or
Walvischvaerder (whaling ship) and Oostvaerder (vessel of the Baltic
Sea) made their appearance.

Small “Spiegelschepen”, having a lighter rig than the others,
appeared elsewhere in the XVIIIth century under the name of _Rinds_
(“Snauschepen”).

Two other types of large fishing vessels for the open sea were built,
viz: the _howker_ or _hoy_ (“Hoeker”) and the _bush_ (“Buys”) which
will be found under the chapter of fishing vessels.

Still another ship comes to us from abroad as a merchantman: the
_Frigate_, while the Tenders (“Boeiers” or “Kromstevens”) had been
imitated already from models of the French navy.

These vessels appeared in the XVIIth century as the result of the
traffic with the city of Rouen (~Witsen~, p. 164, 2ⁿᵈ col.).

From combinations of these types of vessels among each other or
with smaller types have arisen certain kinds of boats called by the
following names: the “Boot”, which was nothing but a small flute having
a “draai-over-boord” stern; the “Hekboot”, derived from the pinnace and
the Galliot; the “Katschip” (cat-boat), from the tender and flute; and
finally the “Stokker”, which had the bow of a “Spiegelship” with the
stern of a howker.

Let it be remarked in passing that it is hard to separate clearly
navigation over seas from navigation along shore, for even small kuffs
(“koffen”) have been chartered for the Indies in many cases.



The distinction made here between navigation over seas and navigation
along shore bears especially on the original destination of the vessels.



~B~) _For navigation along shore._



The largest types of vessels for navigation along shore were
represented by the _galliot_ (“Galjoot”) and the _galeas_ (“Galeas”);
then by the _kuff_ (“Kof”) and the _smack_ (“Smak”).



The “Damloopers”, the “Smalschepen” and the Wijdschepen as well as
the “Friesche turfschepen” (the peat boats of Frisia) belonged to the
family of the smacks.



These boats all came from a single type and differed only in some
detail, of which local needs forced the adoption.



The family of the smacks gave rise to the _hoys_ (“Tjalken”).



The _hoys_ were found especially in Friesland and in Groningen. In the
province of Holland, where they underwent a few slight changes, they
were called Schuiten.



In Zealand, their deck was narrower and they were called “Poonen”.



In North Holland they were designated as “Jacht” (Yachts). Contrary to
what was done for the “Poon”, the bottoms of these boats were not so
wide as those of the hoys. On the Belgian Scheldt, they were rather
finer and known by the name of “Pleiten”, or of “Otters” for the
smallest ones.



Eastern Frisia had similar vessels; they were called “Motten” and bore
some resemblance to the “Kuffs”.



There is still to be found a very old type of merchant vessel,
descended from the old fishing boats and called “Ever” or “Bremerkahn”.



Independently of the family of the hoys, there has existed from the
most distant times, in Overyssel, a distinct type of vessel which in
the XVIIth century, and in Witsen’s time, included the “Potten” and
“Pujen”. Changes were made later in these vessels and they are still
met with at the present time under the name of _Snijboon_ (literally:
French or string bean) from which is descended the pram (“Praam”). The
same shape, but with reduced dimensions, is also found in the “Somp”
and the “Pegge”.



The type of these vessels is distinguished from that of the smacks by
the shape of the bow and stern which are tapering while these parts are
rounded in the smacks.



Many combinations have also been made in this class of vessels; they
have given birth amongst others to the “Koftjalks”, the “Praamaaks” and
the “Aaktjalks”. The _Tenders_ (“Boeiers”) should also be mentioned,
but these vessels had scarce any resemblance to the old “Kromstevens”.



Finally, let the “Kraken” be again mentioned, from which all
characteristics common to the Spanish caracks had disappeared. They
were very strong hoys with quite straight lines, which gave them less
sheer.
